at the end of this lesson we will
discuss some other ipc enhancing
compiler techniques that we will not
discuss in detail but you can find
techniques like this in more advanced
compiler classes the first technique is
software pipelining it's a technique
that helps schedule loops
like these
in a way that doesn't greatly increase
the code size but it allows us to get
the effect of unrolling many times again
i'm not going to discuss this technique
completely but the idea of it is to
treat the loop as a pipeline where this
is the first stage this is the second
stage this is the third stage and so on
and then schedule the code so that we do
the last stage
of a third iteration
while doing the second stage of the next
iteration and the first stage of the
next next iteration why do this this way
well because here we have dependencies
whereas here we don't this store here is
storing a value to which we have been
adding in the previous iteration of the
loop
and this add is using the value that we
have loaded in the previous iteration of
the loop and so on so it kind of forms a
pipeline out of the loop and then it
allows us to do parts of different
iterations concurrently with each other
and another technique that is very
powerful is trace scheduling you can
think of trace scheduling as if
conversion on steroids conceptually we
take a code that has branches because of
if then else's and other things
we find what the common path through
this code is and the blocks that are on
the common path
are then put together like this without
the branches in between now we can
freely schedule instructions in between
these
and we also put checks
if the common path is not being executed
for example here what if this path
should have been executed if that
happens we branch out of this scheduled
code
and at the point when we are branching
out because we have intermixed these
instructions we first have to fix it
basically undo the effects of
instructions that we shouldn't have done
so the compiler needs to create some
code that compensates for that
then we can execute this block that
should have executed and then we execute
the next block that is on the command
path but we cannot execute it here
because we have interchanged these
instructions
and then we can jump to the continuation
of this so simply we form a likely trace
we execute that
with an excellent schedule but any
departure from the trace requires us to
not only execute instructions in a
slightly less efficient way because we
couldn't reschedule as well but also we
need to execute some compensatory code
basically fix things that we messed up
by reordering instructions again this is
not
the full explanation of trace scheduling
i just wanted to give you some idea
about how it works but if you are
interested in techniques like software
pipelining and trace scheduling then i
strongly encourage you to take an
advanced compiler class where these
techniques will be discussed in detail